<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<research_info>

  <!-- Publications -->
  <pub>
    <id>ChildSickness</id>
    <title>Germs in the Family: The Short- and Long-Term Consequences of Intra-Household Disease Spread</title>
    <coauthors>Hui Ding, Maya Rossin-Slater, Hannes Schwandt</coauthors>
        <journal>American Economic Review</journal>
        <vol_issue></vol_issue>
    <date>Conditionally Accepted</date>
    <pages></pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    Preschool-aged children get sick frequently and spread disease to other family members. Despite the universality of this experience, there is limited causal evidence on the magnitudes and consequences of these externalities, especially for infant siblings with developing immune systems and brains. We use Danish administrative data to document that, before age one, younger siblings have 2-3 times higher hospitalization rates for respiratory conditions than older siblings. We combine birth order and within-municipality variation in respiratory disease prevalence among young children, and find lasting differential impacts of early-life respiratory disease exposure on younger siblings’ earnings, educational attainment, chronic respiratory health and mental health-related outcomes.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Child_Sickness.pdf</doc>
  </pub>
  
  <pub>
    <id>breast_cancer</id>
    <title>Do Medical Treatments Work for Work? Evidence from Breast Cancer Patients</title>
    <coauthors>William N. Evans, Mikkel Hasse Pedersen and Mircea Trandafir</coauthors>
    <journal>American Economic Journal: Economic Policy</journal>
        <vol_issue></vol_issue>
    <date>Forthcoming</date>
    <pages></pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    We investigate the effects of radiation therapy on the mortality and economic outcomes of breast cancer patients. We implement a 2SLS strategy within a difference-in-differences framework exploiting variation in treatment stemming from a medical guideline change in Denmark. We reproduce the results from an RCT showing the lifesaving benefits of radiotherapy. We then show radiation therapy also has economic returns: ten years after diagnosis, treatment increases employment by 37% and earnings by 45%. Previous work has documented a substantial employment drop after a breast cancer diagnosis.  Our results imply that radiation therapy can reduce this effect by 70%.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Radiotherapy.pdf</doc>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>autism</id>
    <title>Parental Skills, Assortative Mating, and the Incidence of Autism Spectrum Disorder</title>
    <coauthors>Todd Elder, Scott Imberman, Judy Hellerstein, and Chiara Orsini</coauthors>
    <journal>American Journal of Health Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>10</vol_issue>
    <date>Summer 2024 </date>
    <pages>322–356</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    We assess theories that autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is heritable and transmitted through parental skills using data from Denmark. We construct parental skill measures by mapping Danish occupations to the Occupational Information Network (O*NET) survey of U.S. occupations and principal factor analysis. We find that fathers' skills are linked to ASD in children. A one standard deviation increase in a systems and ordering skills factor correlates with a modest but statistically significant 0.041 percentage-point (2.4%) increase in ASD incidence. There is a negative and slightly larger relationship with communication skills. ASD also is similarly correlated with Deming's (2017) routineness and social skills measures, and fathers again play larger roles. We also find evidence consistent with Baron-Cohen (2002) whereby extreme personality traits in parents affect ASD incidence; having two parents with high systems and ordering relative to communication skills leads to a 35% higher diagnosis rate than having parents with "balanced" skills. While all of these estimates are meaningful given the costs of ASD, they only explain a small fraction of variation in ASD diagnoses. Finally, although assortative mating on skills exists, we cannot detect a role for it in recent dramatic increases in ASD.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Autism.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1086/724794</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>dk_hw_aeapp</id>
    <title>The Correlation of Net and Gross Wealth across Generations: The Role of Parent Income and Child Age </title>
    <coauthors>Mike Lovenheim and David Wasser</coauthors>
    <journal>AEA Papers and Proceedings</journal>
    <vol_issue>112</vol_issue>
    <date>May 2022</date>
    <pages>73-77</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      We use Danish Register Data to examine intergenerational rank-rank correlations in net wealth and gross housing wealth by child age and parental income. Our results indicate that gross housing wealth correlations are more stable by child age than are net wealth correlations, which we argue is due to a downward bias in net wealth correlations from transitory debt. Intergenerational housing wealth correlations also are larger for lower-income families, while net wealth correlations do not vary much across the income distribution. Finally, we show that intergenerational net wealth and gross housing wealth correlations move in opposite directions across the income distribution.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Daysal_HW_AEAPP.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1257/pandp.20221058</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
  <id>bw_spillovers</id>
  <title>Spillover Effects of Early-Life Medical Interventions</title>
  <coauthors>Marianne Simonsen, Mircea Trandafir, and Sanni Breining</coauthors>
   <journal>Review of Economics and Statistics</journal>
  <vol_issue>104</vol_issue>
  <date>January 2022</date>
  <pages>1-16</pages>
  <notes></notes>
  <abstract><![CDATA[
    We investigate the effects of early-life medical treatments on the treated children and their families. We use a regression discontinuity design that exploits changes in medical treatments across the very low birth weight (VLBW) cutoff. Using administrative data from Denmark, we establish that VLBW children have better health and higher test scores. We find that these benefits spill over to other family members: mothers enjoy better mental health and siblings have higher test scores. Maternal mental health improvements seem to be driven by better focal child health, and sibling spillovers by improved interactions within the family and parental compensating behavior. 
  ]]></abstract>
  <doc>BW_Spillovers.pdf</doc>
  <doi>https://doi.org/10.1162/rest_a_00982</doi>
</pub>

<pub>
    <id>dk_housing_fertility</id>
    <title>Home Prices, Fertility, and Early-Life Health Outcomes</title>
    <coauthors>Mike Lovenheim, Nikolaj Siersbæk, and David Wasser</coauthors>
    <journal>Journal of Public Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>198</vol_issue>
    <date>June 2021</date>
    <pages>104366</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      We estimate the effect of housing price changes on fertility and early-life child health in Denmark. Using rich population register data among women aged 20-44 who own a home, we find that for each 100,000 DKK increase in home prices (equivalent to $12,000), the likelihood of giving birth increases by 0.27 percentage points or 2.35%. These estimates are similar to findings from the US per dollar of home price change, which is surprising given the strong pro-natalist policies and generous government programs in Denmark. We also present the first estimates of the effect of home prices on infant health. Our findings indicate that housing price increases lead to better child health at birth in terms of low birth weight and prematurity, however most of these effects reflect changes in the composition of births. There is no evidence of an effect on health during the first five years of life. These findings are consistent with both children and child health being normal goods that are similarly-valued in the US and Denmark.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Housing_Fertility.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2021.104366</doi>
  </pub>

<pub>
    <id>nl_gyn</id>
    <title>Low-risk isn't no-risk: Perinatal treatments and the health of low-income newborns</title>
    <coauthors>Mircea Trandafir and Reyn van Ewijk</coauthors>
    <journal>Journal of Health Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>64</vol_issue>
    <date>March 2019</date>
    <pages>55-67</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      We investigate the effects of perinatal medical treatments on low-income newborns who are classified as low-risk. A policy rule in The Netherlands states that low-risk deliveries before week 37 should be supervised by physicians and later deliveries only by midwives with no physician present. This creates large discontinuities in the probability of receiving medical interventions only physicians are allowed to perform. Using a regression discontinuity design, we find that babies born slightly before the week-37 cutoff are significantly less likely to die than babies born slightly later. Our data suggest that physician supervision of birth reduces the likelihood of adverse events such as fetal distress or emergency C-section. Our results indicate that low-income women benefit from receiving a higher level of medical care even if no explicit risk factors have been recognized, pointing to challenges in identifying all high-risk pregnancies. "Back-of-the-envelope" calculations suggest this additional care is highly cost-effective.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>GYN_Midwife.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhealeco.2019.01.006</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>nl_homebirths</id>
    <title>Saving Lives at Birth: The Impact of Homebirths on Infant Outcomes</title>
    <coauthors>Mircea Trandafir and Reyn van Ewijk</coauthors>
    <journal>American Economic Journal: Applied Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>7:3</vol_issue>
    <date>July 2015</date>
    <pages>28–50</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      Many developed countries have recently experienced sharp increases in home birth rates. This paper investigates the impact of home births on the health of low-risk newborns using data from the Netherlands, the only developed country where home births are widespread. To account for endogeneity in location of birth, we exploit the exogenous variation in distance from a mother's residence to the closest hospital. We find that giving birth in a hospital leads to substantial reductions in newborn mortality. We provide suggestive evidence that proximity to medical technologies may be an important channel contributing to these health gains.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>NL_Homebirths_Manuscript.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1257/app.20120359</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>meno_spillover</id>
    <title>Spillover Effects of Drug Safety Warnings on Preventive Health Care Use</title>
    <coauthors>Chiara Orsini</coauthors>
    <journal>B.E. Journal of Economic Analysis and Policy</journal>
    <vol_issue>15:1</vol_issue>
    <date>January 2015</date>
    <pages>179-208</pages>
    <notes><![CDATA[
      <span style="font-size=70%;">Earlier versions of this paper circulated as "Spillover Effects of Drug Safety Warnings on Health Behavior"</span>
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      We examine how new medical information on drug safety impacts preventive health care use. We exploit the release of the findings of the Women's Health Initiative Study (WHIS) -- the largest randomized controlled trial of women's health -- which demonstrated in 2002 the health risks associated with the long-term use of Hormone Replacement Therapy (HRT). We first show that, after the release of the WHIS findings, HRT use dropped sharply among post-menopausal women. We then estimate the spillover effects of the WHIS findings on preventive care by means of a difference-in-differences methodology comparing changes in preventive care use among 60 to 69 year-old women (who have high rates of HRT use) with the change among women aged 75 and above (who have much lower rates of HRT use). Using data from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System for the period 1998-2007, we find that women aged 60-69 had statistically and economically significant declines in their annual mammography checks, checkups, cholesterol checks and blood stool tests, when compared to older women.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>WHIS_Behavior.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1515/bejeap-2013-0038</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>bilingual</id>
    <title>Impact of Bilingual Education Programs on Limited English Proficient Students and Their Peers: Regression Discontinuity Evidence from Texas</title>
    <coauthors>Aimee Chin and Scott Imberman</coauthors>
    <journal>Journal of Public Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>107</vol_issue>
    <date>November 2013</date>
    <pages>63-78</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      Texas requires a school district to offer bilingual education when its enrollment of limited English proficient (LEP) students in a particular elementary grade and language is twenty or higher. Using school panel data, we find a significant increase in the probability that a district provides bilingual education above this 20-student cutoff. Using this discontinuity as an instrument for district bilingual education provision, we find that providing bilingual education programs (relative to providing only English as a Second Language programs) does not significantly impact the standardized test scores of students with Spanish as their home language (comprised primarily of ever-LEP students). However, we find significant positive impacts on non-LEP students’ achievement, which indicates that education programs for LEP students have spillover effects to non-LEP students.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>bilingual_ed_texas_aug2013.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpubeco.2013.08.008</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>CaUninsurance</id>
    <title>Does Uninsurance Affect the Health Outcomes of the Insured? Evidence from Heart Attack Patients in California</title>
    <journal>Journal of Health Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>31:4</vol_issue>
    <date>July 2012</date>
    <pages>545-563</pages>
    <notes><![CDATA[
      <span style="font-size=70%;">Mentioned in <a href="http://purl.access.gpo.gov/GPO/LPS113886"
        target="_new">"The Economic Case For Health Care Reform"</a> (Council of Economic Advisers).</span>
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      In this paper, I examine the impact of uninsured patients on the health of the insured, focusing on one health outcome -- the in-hospital mortality rate of insured heart attack patients. I employ panel data models using patient discharge and hospital financial data from California (1999-2006). My results indicate that uninsured patients have an economically significant effect that increases the mortality rate of insured heart attack patients. I show that these results are not driven by alternative explanations, including reverse causality, patient composition effects, sample selection or unobserved trends and that they are robust to a host of specification checks. My results also indicate that the primary channel for the observed spillover effects is increased hospital uncompensated care costs. Although data limitations constrain my capacity to check how hospitals change their provision of care to insured heart attack patients in response to reduced revenues, the evidence I have suggests a modest increase in the quantity of cardiac services without a corresponding increase in hospital staff.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Daysal_CaliUninsAMI.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhealeco.2012.04.004</doi>
  </pub>

  <pub>
    <id>emp_subs_turkey</id>
    <title>Do Employment Subsidies Work? Evidence from Regionally Targeted Subsidies in Turkey</title>
    <coauthors>Gordon Betcherman and Carmen Pages</coauthors>
    <journal>Labour Economics</journal>
    <vol_issue>17:4</vol_issue>
    <date>August 2010</date>
    <pages>710-722</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      This paper studies the effects on registered employment and number of registered establishments of two employment subsidy schemes in Turkey. We implement a difference-in-differences methodology to construct appropriate counterfactuals for the covered provinces. Our findings suggest that both subsidy programs did lead to significant net increases in registered jobs in eligible provinces (5%-13% for the first program and 11%-15% for the second). However, the cost of the actual job creation was high because of substantial deadweight losses, particularly for the first program (47% and 78%). Because of better design features, the second subsidy program had lower, though still significant, deadweight losses (27%-46%). Although constrained by data availability, the evidence suggests that the dominant effect of subsidies was to increase social security registration of firms and workers rather than boosting total employment and economic activity. This supports the theory that in countries with weak enforcement institutions, high labor taxes on low-wage workers may lead to substantial incentives for firms and workers to operate informally.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Regional_Incentives.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.labeco.2009.12.002</doi>
  </pub>


  <!-- Comments and Invited Policy Briefs -->

    <opub>
    <id>iza_labor_2</id>
    <title>Early-Life Medical Care and Human Capital Accumulation: Update</title>
    <coauthors>Jonas Cuzulan Hirani</coauthors>
    <journal>IZA World of Labor</journal>
    <vol_issue>217v2</vol_issue>
    <date>September 2021</date>
    <pages></pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Daysal_WoL_2.pdf</doc>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.15185/izawol.217.v2</doi>
  </opub>

  <opub>
    <id>bjog_comment</id>
    <title>Re: A recent study by economists on the impact of home births on infant outcomesconfuses the debate on home birth</title>
    <coauthors>Mircea Trandafir and Reyn van Ewijk</coauthors>
    <journal>BJOG: An International Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal>
    <vol_issue>123:10</vol_issue>
    <date>September 2016</date>
    <pages>1713-1714</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      Our reply to the letter by de Jonge et al (2016) on how to interpret our findings related to
      the effect of a hospital birth on low-risk newborn mortality in the context of the home birth
      debate.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>BJOG_letter.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1471-0528.14250</doi>
  </opub>

  <opub>
    <id>medisch</id>
    <title>Thuisbevalling  riskanter  in  arm  gezin</title>
    <coauthors>Mircea Trandafir and Reyn van Ewijk</coauthors>
    <journal>Medisch  Contact</journal>
    <vol_issue>13</vol_issue>
    <date>2016</date>
    <pages>16-18</pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      A summary of our findings on the effects of a hospital birth on low-risk newborn mortality. (In Dutch)
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Medisch_Contact.pdf</doc>
    <doi>https://goo.gl/TV3WiR</doi>
  </opub>

  <opub>
    <id>iza_labor</id>
    <title>Early-Life Medical Care and Human Capital Accumulation</title>
    <coauthors></coauthors>
    <journal>IZA World of Labor</journal>
    <vol_issue>217</vol_issue>
    <date>December 2015</date>
    <pages></pages>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Daysal_WoL.pdf</doc>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.15185/izawol.217</doi>
  </opub>

	<!-- Working papers -->

      <wp>
    <id>AD</id>
    <title>Antidepressant Treatment in Childhood</title>
    <coauthors>Sonia Bhalotra, Mircea Trandafir</coauthors>
    <date>July 2025</date>
    <notes><![CDATA[
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    Mental health disorders tend to emerge in childhood, with half starting by age %&. This makes
early intervention important, but treatment rates are low, and antidepressant treatment for children remains controversial since an FDA warning in "##& that highlighted adverse effects. Linking individuals across Danish administrative registers, we provide some of the first evidence of
impacts of antidepressant treatment in childhood on objectively measured mental health indicators and economic outcomes over time, and the !rst attempt to investigate under- vs over-
treatment. Leveraging conditional random assignment of patients to psychiatrists with different prescribing tendencies, we find that treatment during ages 8-15 improves test scores at age 16, particularly in Math, increases enrollment in post-compulsory education at age 18, and that
it leads to higher employment and earnings and lower welfare dependence at ages 25-30. We
demonstrate, on average, a reduction in suicide attempts, self-harm, and hospital visits following AD initiation. The gains to treatment are, in general, larger for low SES children, but they
are less likely to be treated. Using a marginal treatment effects framework and Math scores as the
focal outcome, we show positive returns to treatment among the untreated. Policy simulations
confirm that expanding treatment among low SES children (and boys) generates substantial net
benefits, consistent with under-treatment in these groups. Our !ndings underscore the potential of early mental health treatment to improve longer term economic outcomes and reducing
inequality.    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>AD.pdf</doc>
  </wp>

    <wp>
    <id>child_disability</id>
    <title>Child Disability and Effects on Sibling Mental Health</title>
    <coauthors>Janet Currie, Mette Gørtz, and Jonas Hirani</coauthors>
    <date>December 2024</date>
    <notes><![CDATA[
    NBER Working Paper No. 33303.
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    Mental health disorders are the leading cause of childhood disability worldwide. We examine the impact of a relatively common household stressor on child mental health: the presence of a younger sibling with a physical disability. Using Danish administrative data from families with at least 3 children, we focus on differences between first and second born children in families with and without a 3rd child with a disability.  Second-born children in these families spend a larger fraction of their early childhood in families that may be under stress. We find that second-born children are 11 percent more likely to use mental health services than first-born children.  There is a 19% increase in psychiatric visits and a 16% increase in use of psychiatric medications. These results are confirmed by matching models.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>ChildDisability.pdf</doc>
  </wp>
  
    <wp>
    <id>ChildCancer</id>
    <title>Child Health, Parental Well-Being, and the Social Safety Net</title>
    <coauthors>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Snaebjorn Gunnsteinsson, Teresa Molina, Herdis Steingrimsdottir</coauthors>
    <date>December 2024</date>
    <notes>NBER Working Paper No. 31277</notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    How do parents contend with threats to the health and survival of their children? Can the social safety net mitigate the negative economic effects on affected families? We study these questions by combining the universe of cancer diagnoses among Danish children with register data for affected and matched unaffected families. Parental income declines substantially for 3-4 years following a child's cancer diagnosis. Fathers' incomes eventually recover fully, but mothers' incomes remain 3% lower 12 years after diagnosis. Using a policy reform that increased the generosity of targeted safety net transfers to affected families, we show that such transfers play a crucial role in smoothing income and, importantly, do not generate work disincentive effects; indeed, if anything, mothers' labor market outcomes improve as a result of the additional generosity. Mental health and fertility effects are large, but are not likely mediators for impacts on economic outcomes. The overall pattern of results is most consistent with the idea that parents' preferences to personally provide care for and spend time with their sick children are strong enough that additional work disincentives created by the generosity of the safety net are essentially irrelevant. This makes timely transfers to affected families an effective policy tool for smoothing income during the critical years following the onset of a severe health shock to children.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>ChildhoodCancer.pdf</doc>
  </wp>

    <wp>
    <id>PillMH</id>
    <title>The Oral Contraceptive Pill, Adolescents' Mental Health and Socio-Economic Outcomes</title>
    <coauthors>Ana Costa-Ramón and  Ana Rodríguez-González</coauthors>
    <date>July 2025</date>
    <notes><![CDATA[
    IZA Working Paper No. 16288.
    <br> Revise and Resubmit at the <b>Economic Journal</b>
    <br> Press Coverage: <a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/oral-contraceptive-pill-and-adolescents-mental-health" target=_blank>VoxEU</a>
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    This paper examines the mental health and socio-economic effects of oral contraceptive use among adolescents. Using Danish administrative data and two complementary
identification strategies - an event study and provider prescribing variation - we find
that initiation of the combined pill leads to short-run increases in psychiatric contacts,
depression diagnoses, and antidepressant use. Evidence points to a biological mechanism rather than increased detection. Despite these short-term effects, we find no
impact on academic performance, educational attainment, or labor market outcomes.
Our findings highlight an important trade-off in adolescent contraceptive care.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>PillMH.pdf</doc>
  </wp>

  <wp>
    <id>HWTransmission</id>
    <title>The Intergenerational Transmission of Housing Wealth</title>
    <coauthors>Michael F. Lovenheim and David N. Wasser</coauthors>
    <date>July 2025</date>
    <notes><![CDATA[
    NBER Working Paper No. 31669. 
    <br> Press Coverage: <a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/intergenerational-transmission-housing-wealthe" target=_blank>VoxEU</a>
    ]]></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    Rising wealth inequality has spurred an increased interest in understanding how and why
wealth is correlated across generations. We exploit plausibly exogenous variation in housing
wealth driven by home value changes in different areas to isolate the causal impact of parental
housing wealth during different childhood periods on children’s long-run wealth accumulation.
Using population-level Danish administrative data, we find that 27% and 25% of each Krone of
parental housing wealth change during early-childhood is transmitted to children’s overall and
housing wealth in adulthood, respectively. The corresponding transmission rates for parental
housing wealth changes during middle-childhood are 25% and 15%, with a transmission to non-
housing wealth of 10%. There is little evidence of transmission of parental housing wealth
changes that occur during the teenage years. Examining mechanisms, we find that earnings
and educational attainment can explain only 20-30% of the intergenerational transmission of
parental wealth gains. We argue that the transmission of parental housing wealth changes in
childhood are driven in large part by changes to unobserved household environment and parental
behaviors that are passed on to children and shape their savings behavior in adulthood.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>HWTransmission.pdf</doc>
  </wp>

  <wp>
    <id>screening</id>
    <title>An Economic Approach to Machine Learning in Health Policy</title>
    <coauthors>Sendhil Mullainathan, Ziad Obermeyer, Suproteem K. Sarkar, Mircea Trandafir</coauthors>
    <date>January 2024</date>
    <notes></notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
    We consider the health effects of "precision" screening policies for cancer guided by algorithms. We show that machine learning models that predict breast cancer from health claims data outperform models based on just age and established risk factors. We estimate that screening women with high predicted risk of invasive tumors would reduce the long-run incidence of later-stage tumors by 40%. Screening high-risk women would also lead to half the rate of cancer overdiagnosis that screening low-risk women would. We show that these results depend crucially on the machine learning model’s prediction target. A model trained to predict positive mammography results leads to policies with weaker health effects and higher rates of overdiagnosis than a model trained to predict invasive tumors.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>Screening.pdf</doc>
  </wp>


  <wp>
    <id>hrt</id>
    <title>The Miracle Drugs: Hormone Replacement Therapy and Labor Market Behavior of Middle Aged Women</title>
    <coauthors>Chiara Orsini</coauthors>
    <date>Revised February 2014</date>
    <notes>IZA Working Paper No. 7993.</notes>
    <abstract><![CDATA[
      In an aging society, determining which factors contribute to the employment of older individuals is increasingly important. We examine the impact of medical innovations on the employment of middle-aged women focusing on the specific case of Hormone Replacement Therapy (HRT), a common treatment for the alleviation of negative menopausal symptoms. HRT medications were among the most popular prescriptions in the United States until 2002 when the Women’s Health Initiative Study – the largest randomized control trial on women ever undertaken – documented the health risks associated with their long term use. We exploit the release of these findings within a Fixed Effect Instrumental Variable framework to address the endogeneity in HRT use. Our results indicate substantial benefits of HRT use to the short-term employment of middle-aged women.
    ]]></abstract>
    <doc>WHIS_Labor.pdf</doc>
  </wp>


</research_info>
